Knitting a proper swatch is the key
to success with your knitting machine.
Follow along as I knit a swatch.
This is my LK 150 and I'm knitting
stockinette, but the process is the same
for all machines and stitch patterns.
Here are suggestions
for stitch and row counts.
No matter how you plan to measure your
gauge either using a regular
ruler or gauge rulers.
You will be measuring a specific number of
stitches and rows within a larger piece.
Measuring within a larger piece allows
for accurate measurement without
the distortion of the edges.
Here are some suggestions.
If you're using gauge rulers
for a blue ruler cast on 30 stitches.
This would be maybe for a bulky machine.
For a green ruler cast on 60
stitches for a standard machine.
For the yellow ruler cast on 50 stitches
for a mid gauge machine.
Of course, you could cast on a 100
stitches and knit a 100 rows as long as
you have more stitches and rows
than you're going to be measuring.
Use the cast on method of your choice.
Just get some stitches on the machine.
I pulled every other needle and worked
an e wrap cast on over every other needle.
Next, thread the carriage.
Wiggle and pull to confirm
that it's threaded correctly.
The yarn is not hung up
and it will flow smoothly.
When you are sure that the carriage is
threaded correctly
pull down on the working yarn
in the back to take up any slack.
You can hang your cast on comb now.
I knit 1 row first and then added
my cast on comb and a single weight.
Knit a few rows and end
with the carriage on the right.
Remove the working yarn from the carriage,
but don't break it or cut it. Just
loop it over the edge of the machine.
Thread up a contrasting color of similar
weight and wiggle and pull to confirm that
it is threaded in the carriage correctly.
If not, you run the risk of dropping
all the stitches off the machine.
Now I like to hang a clothespin or a chip
clip to add some weight
to the tail of yarn.
Knit 2 rows with the contrasting yarn.
Break that waste yarn
and secure it with the clip.
Using the clip ensures
that the end stitches knit well.
Set your row counter to 000.
Re thread the main yarn in the carriage,
wiggle and pull to make sure
that that yarn is inserted correctly
and if you need to, reach back
and pull down to take up any slack.
Knit a few rows and place some markers.
Markers are just a short piece
of contrasting color yarn
created with a slip knot.
Knit to the row where you want the marker.
The markers will isolate the number
of stitches you'll be measuring.
For example, I'm going
to be measuring 30 stitches.
So I'll place my marker on needles
number 16 left and 16 right.
This isolates the center 30 stitches.
To place a marker put the loop
of the marker in the hook of the needle.
Pull out the needle so the stitch falls
behind the latch and then pull
the marker through the stitch.
Stitch.
In other words, manually knit
a stitch with the marker loop.
Do this on both sides.
Then continue knitting the number
of rows you'll be measuring.
Remove the main yarn
from the feeder but don't cut it.
Loop it around the end of your machine.
Then thread up the contrasting
yarn again and knit 2 rows.
Remember to wiggle and pull to make
sure the carriage is threaded correctly.
We don't want everything
dropping off the machine.
Knit 2 marker rows with the waste
yarn and break that contrasting color.
Re thread the main yarn,
wiggle and pull and knit 2 or 3 rows.
Next, we'll mark our swatch
with the number of our carriage tension.
I'm using tension 6
so I'll create 6 eyelets so I have
a permanent record of the tension.
To make an eyelet, use your single prong
transfer tool and remove
a stitch to the tool.
Transfer that stitch to its neighbor.
You'll empty the needle.
Skip a needle and repeat across
for the number of eyelets that you need.
Be sure to put all those empty
needles back into working position.
We want to just create some
eyelets but continue knitting.
On the LK150
and some other machines you can set up
the tension dial to somewhere
between 6 and 7 for example.
I might have used 6.5 or 6+.
In that case, I would put 6 eyelets,
skip a few needles and then
add an additional eyelet.
Establish a code for yourself,
whatever works, so you can see exactly the
setting if you look a few months later.
After you form all your eyelets please be
sure to make sure all your
needles are in working position.
Knit a few more rows and then bind off.
I'm using my favorite bind off.
I'm manually knitting that last
row with fairly large loops.
Put the yarn in the hooks of the needles
and manually knit each 1 of the stitches.
To prepare for the bind off, carefully
pull all the needles all the way out.
I'll pull loop through loop to bind off.
Use whatever bind off method you like.
Swatches are a great opportunity to learn
and practice different bind
off and cast on methods.
Use the tail of yarn
to finish off the last stitch.
With the swatch off the machine
and the ends secure you can now wash your
swatch, block it and use whatever methods
you'll be using for your finished garment.
This is called dressing your swatch.
It's a good time to discover
how the yarn behaves.
Now don't measure your
swatch right off the machine.
Let it rest at least
24 hours then dress it.
You might want to let it
rest a little bit again.
Your next step is to use a regular ruler
or a gauge ruler to establish your gauge.
I suggest attaching a string tag to record
your machine, tension,
gauge, dressing method, and any
other notes about your swatch.
Knitting a proper swatch is the secret
to successful machine knitting.